<definition-page last-updated="2025-09-11" page-url="https://medlineplus.gov/xml/fitnessdefinitions.xml" title="Definitions of Health Terms: Fitness"><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health-topics/physical-activity-and-your-heart"><term><![CDATA[>Activity Count]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Physical activity is any body movement that works your muscles and requires more energy than resting. Walking, running, dancing, swimming, yoga, and gardening are a few examples of physical activity.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health-topics/physical-activity-and-your-heart#Types"><term><![CDATA[>Aerobic Exercise]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Aerobic exercise is activity that moves your large muscles, such as those in your arms and legs.  It makes you breathe harder and your heart beat faster.  Examples include running, swimming, walking, and biking.  Over time, regular aerobic activity makes your heart and lungs stronger and able to work better.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="NIH MedlinePlus" reference-url=""><term><![CDATA[>Basal Metabolic Rate]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Basal metabolic rate is the measure of the energy necessary for maintaining basic functions, such as breathing, heart rate, and digestion.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/educational/lose_wt/risk.htm"><term><![CDATA[>Body Mass Index]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Body Mass Index (BMI) is an estimate of your body fat.  It is calculated from your height and weight.  It can tell you whether you are underweight, normal, overweight, or obese. It can help you gauge your risk for diseases that can occur with more body fat. ]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/public/heart/phy_active.pdf"><term><![CDATA[>Cool Down]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Your physical activity session should end by gradually slowing down. You can also cool down by changing to a less vigorous activity, such as moving from jogging to walking. This process allows your body to relax gradually.  A cool down can last 5 minutes or more.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases" reference-url=""><term><![CDATA[>Energy Balance]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>The balance between calories you get from eating and drinking and those you use up through physical activity and body processes like breathing, digesting food, and, in children, growing.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/educational/wecan/healthy-weight-basics/balance.htm"><term><![CDATA[>Energy Consumed]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Energy is another word for calories. What you eat and drink is "energy in." What you burn through physical activity is "energy out."]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/public/heart/phy_active.pdf"><term><![CDATA[>Flexibility  (Training)]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Flexibility training is exercise that stretches and lengthens your muscles. It can help improve your joint flexibility and keep your muscles limber.  This can help prevent injuries. Some examples are yoga, tai chi, and pilates.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health-topics/how-heart-works"><term><![CDATA[>Heart Rate]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Heart rate, or pulse, is how many times your heart beats in a period of time — usually a minute. The usual pulse for an adult is 60 to 100 beats per minute after resting for at least 10 minutes.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/resources/heart/obesity-guide-physical-active-html"><term><![CDATA[>Maximum Heart Rate]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>The maximum heart rate is the fastest your heart can beat.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="NIH MedlinePlus" reference-url="https://medlineplus.gov/sweat.html"><term><![CDATA[>Perspiration]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Perspiration, or sweat, is a clear, salty liquid produced by glands in your skin.   It is how your body cools itself.  Sweating a lot is normal when it is hot or when you exercise, feel anxious, or have a fever. It can also happen during menopause.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases" reference-url=""><term><![CDATA[>Strength Training]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Strength training, or resistance training, is exercise that works your muscles by making you push or pull against something. It strengthens your muscles and can improve your bone strength and balance. Some examples are lifting weights, working with resistance bands, and doing push-ups and pull-ups.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/health/resources/heart/obesity-guide-physical-active-html"><term><![CDATA[>Target Heart Rate]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Your target heart rate is a percentage of your maximum heart rate, which is the fastest your heart can beat.  It is based on your age.  The activity level that is best for your health uses 50–75 percent of your maximum heart rate. This range is your target heart rate zone.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute" reference-url="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/files/docs/public/heart/phy_active.pdf"><term><![CDATA[>Warm Up ]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Your physical activity session should start at a slow-to-medium pace to give your body a chance to get ready for more vigorous movement. A warm up should last about 5 to 10 minutes.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="NIH MedlinePlus" reference-url="https://medlineplus.gov/dehydration.html"><term><![CDATA[>Water Intake]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>We all need to drink water. How much you need depends on your size, activity level, and the weather where you live. Keeping track of your water intake helps make sure that you get enough. Your intake includes fluids that you drink, and fluids you get from food.]]></definition></term-group><term-group reference="NIH MedlinePlus" reference-url=""><term><![CDATA[>Weight (Body Mass) ]]></term><definition><![CDATA[>Your weight is the mass or quantity of your heaviness.  It is expressed by units of pounds or kilograms.]]></definition></term-group></definition-page> 